okay here we go we're at chur Dam chur
Dam where's the confuser guys I
think yeah chy dumic means
uh all the advises here it means advises
generally dtic means like a pledge but
here it means
uh advises of chi means Dharma in
general General Dharma advices try to
keep them and
specifically uh your
promise to treat other people the same
as you treat yourself that's
all okay those two
commitments okay that
commitment this language is very very
famous when you take a vow and you
say means I will keep it I will keep
this commitment so d means at the cost
of my life at the cost of my life then
there's these very romantic
movies did you see the shanang movie
from China it's pretty
good uh shang's story from China good
they did a good
job and uh when they teach
this part of the L room they say if
somebody grab you and put a knife to
your neck and say will you give up the
loj you have to say no then
they okay
unfortunately you cannot meet this very
often you know like it doesn't really
happen you know most people don't care
at all what you
do and uh that knife is
just coffee and cinnamon rolls and
Netflix okay Netflix is the knife okay
like some people lose their life to
Netflix and to coffee shop and things
like that you know you I don't think In
Our
Lifetime there will be some kind of
Revolution and all the Buddhist people
will have to swear to give up Buddhism
die it's very romantic if you get a
chance good luck I suspect we won't die
uh but every day you have the same
Choice Netflix has live here you know
and uh every day you have the same
Choice give up your life or or give the
or the Dharma you know which one which
one will you choose okay the
quiet Netflix every day quiet waste time
every day that's how most Buddhists die
you know they their practice killed by
that okay by Netflix okay that's why we
are sneaking into
Netflix okay all right
um I'm not supposed to fundraise for
that right s I'm not supposed to tell
them we have to pay H some of the we
have to pay some of the Netflix money to
to get into Netflix do you understand
what I'm
saying but this is ACI so I cannot
fundraise for s
project but he's right here in the white
shirt uh and it's an expensive it's an
expensive project and all the world
viiew organizations it's supposed to
help
everybody it's supposed to help all of
our organizations so sometime I'll
fundra for it if if you would rather
just talk to him privately that's
okay all
right say
kaas uh Kawa means hard to do difficult
to do okay difficult to do Kawa and uh
this means there are three difficult
things to do kaum and by the way all of
this
section is like
little you know advice is like the three
toughs the three tough things and then
there's going to be the two exciting
things and there's going to be the four
you know like that okay and then they
just go very fast I think he's getting
impatient to reach the six Perfections
okay and starts to speed up if you're
very sensitive with scripture you can
feel it it's called tbu say
tbu yeah Nick knows it's called a horse
race when the Llama is running out of
time because he talked too much about
fundraising then they start to teach
faster and faster okay they call tub I
feel he's doing tub here
okay uh this we had it
yesterday we had the present tense
yesterday and it was identify or
recognize something and here it
says what's it
mean it's hard to catch when you're
having a clesia clesia means negative
emotion I couldn't find a good English
word it's anger desire hatred irritation
unhappy blah blah okay clay I call claa
okay mental so unhappy thought okay bad
attitude and he says they are difficult
to recognize when you're having them
why because you're having
one when you have one it messes up your
mind and it's messes up your mind so you
can't recognize that you're having one
it's cute
right negative emotion has a special
self-preservation
technique when you get angry you truly
believe you're are not
angry uh when you have bad desire you
truly believe you're are not having bad
desire you know you're sitting there at
the cake shop in the okuro hotel
downstairs first floor in the middle on
the right
side and you looking at apple
tart and you're like I don't have clich
cu the appeti to took control of your
mind already when you have claure you
don't know you have CL okay so it's
difficult to know when you have a
negative thought in your mind because
the negative thought in your mind
changes your mind and you can't recog
you can't see yourself okay second
one what's
nambo yeah the antidote you know like
the antidote for apple pie is to eat it
quickly and then it's not there
anymore uh right rob me me and Rob
worked on one uh it's difficult to think
of the antidote when you're in the
middle of a when you feel angry at
somebody it's impossible to to think
about patience it's not possible okay
third one gun chawa this gun by the way
the Sanskrit is $100
gun what's a
Sanskrit gun or
G Tantra the the the Sanskrit is Tantra
okay $100 for Nick okay
[Applause]
yeah to get your surfboard uh yeah so
Tantra means flow Tanta means the flow
right uh it can mean secret teachings
but usually the word means flow okay
Tantra and
here means you know
from to cut yeah so to cut the Tantra
means to cut the flow is when you're in
a anger attack or jealousy attack or
upset attack
or apple pie attack right ra then it's
so very difficult to interrupt it okay
it's usually you only realize you had it
the next day like 24 hours after it
finishes you say oh I got angry
yesterday or I ate six apple pies
yesterday usually you only understand
the next day okay so Guk Kawa means
these are the three kaas it's it's
difficult to know when you're having a
CLA attack it's difficult to to apply
the
antidote and it's very difficult to cut
flow before it runs its natural course
before it ends by itself which sometimes
can take 10 years if it's a
divorce okay it's diff it takes a long
time to cut those naturally okay they
just run out of power right n nen means
work hard
work hard sheer love understand the
nature of your mind when you're having
negative thoughts study your mind like a
scientist you know study your own mind
there's a lot to learn about your own
attitudes about your own moods get to
know your moods get to know how to stop
your mind when it don't let your mind
push you
around okay the mind can be like uh I
have the friend next door he has this
big dog the dog's name is
Winston okay and uh he's really mean and
big you know and when he gets off the
Rope you're like I just run into my
house and he has a crush on my wife I'm
kind
of jealous of Winston cuz she she just
gives him treats every day and he has a
crush on he's he comes by house and he's
like you know and your mind is like a
big powerful dog and your mind is like
that you have to put a rope on your mind
and you have to control it okay don't
Let It Go by itself okay you got to
control your mind you have to learn to
get to know your mind okay it's very
difficult it's very very difficult
everybody goes to the gym to build up
their muscles you know look nice
nice and then they let their mind do
whatever the hell it wants you know what
I mean and it's ugly the mind is ugly
you know their their body is very
beautiful and their mind is ugly so I
think my policy is eat apple pie let the
body do anything try to keep the Mind
beautiful okay all right got it no you
should have beautiful body and Beautiful
Mind okay both both you should do Lama d
uh there's a picture now
of yeah this is the right picture yeah
you guys got it yeah uh I used to be in
the Boy Scouts I'm a eagle scout by the
way which is the highest and it takes
like many years and when you reach Eagle
Scout uh there's a secret award after
that and I'm not supposed to talk about
it but don't tell anybody it's called
order of the arrow and it's a secret uh
test they give a test and when you
finish Boy Scouts maybe you
are maybe you're about 13 years old or
something and then if
you if you if if you I don't know if
your teacher thinks you're you're
qualified they have a special test and
they take you way out in the
mountains and uh they give you two
matches and they give you a
knife and they say three days later you
know they say see you in three days or
four days and uh it's hard it's really
hard you burn the first two matches
immediately cuz it's
cold and and it's really cool it's a
cool test for young for young people and
it's pretty serious and
uh to get to the mountains you have to
ride a horse you you have to you have to
put the supplies on a horse or or a a
donkey br br is better horse looks nice
B carries
more uh but buo is a real excuse me
that's why they call them ass
maybe uh they are
very grumpy
and uh but you you put everything on
them they carry like they can carry five
people's load you know and uh they're
very it's nice to have one if you're
going far it's nice to have bir so
here's a Lo it's the next one is called
uh loading your supplies the next part
of the
lojo is called loading your supplies
which is called uh uh Z okay in in in
toban it's
called
Uh uh Lama SEL number one uh try to meet
a good teacher and
and be picky about your teacher be super
picky okay they say don't be like a
hungry dog that finds a dog
biscuit you know they say be a little
picky you know so be picky in advance
okay it's very bad luck to meet a
teacher study with a teacher and then
decide you don't like them uh it's
better to check them first
and a good a good uh a good way is to
ask other people ask other people you
know did you study with this person are
they honest uh are they a good person
you know and check with the students I
like to check the students if the
students are all Angry stupid people
probably the teachers didn't do a good
job I you know check a teacher carefully
and it's okay to go to many teachers try
many teachers uh but don't
commit until you check them okay what's
the story gishi Michael always tells for
$100 jeans $100
yeah so my wife is super super beautiful
that's why I chase her for 50 years and
uh 53 and um I took her to the jean
store the cowboy store in
Cottonwood and uh she wants to buy a
pair of
jeans
and and I always tell people that story
I hate that story many stores like
Sephora they don't have place where the
boyfriend can sit down you have to stand
up it's like church or something you
know and uh I have to stand up and wait
for her she tried on
41 pairs of
jeans okay I
counted uh guess how money she
bought yeah she said let's go to the
other store I'm like I almost got angry
and I'm
like you know like that but that's how
you should pick your teacher you should
be picky go try 42
teachers no try it's a lifetime
commitment it's a big commitment uh
don't take a teacher easily and so you
can go to the store that's fine how can
you try never ever buy jeans online it's
so stupid you know go to the store try
them on okay I don't care what size they
put in the Internet it's always wrong
okay you try it on and two people can
put in the gene or half people can put
in the gene you know so go
and try the teacher try for a while say
I'm not committing I just want to check
you out you know there in the ancient
times there's a tradition to check for
12 years check the teacher for 12 years
there's a very famous joke one student
went to the teacher and said I'm
watching you for 12 years and you pass
you're you're a you're a good teacher I
I'm gonna be your student and he said
let me check you for 12
years teacher said let me check you for
12 years so was 24 years
anyway uh don't be afraid to check okay
don't anytime you buy something and the
salesperson rush you you're going to
make a mistake like if you buy a new car
uh if the salesperson is very pushy
don't buy it means there's something
wrong with the car okay you know if the
salesp person like I don't care if you
buy it I got 200 other people want to
buy it then you should buy
it okay so don't don't rush it you know
don't let the Lama rashio okay just that
I'm checking you out and check them out
and don't be shy it's a tradition they
should accept that if the Llama doesn't
let you check them then I would try a
different one I would try somebody else
the good llama should say check me go
ahead check it check talk to my students
everything check the internet look
everywhere and and and take me if you if
you find out I'm a good llama take me if
not find someone who fit you every
person has a different
pigle right
bottom how do you say
pusi
push po how do you
know okay anyway everybody's but is
different size so maybe one teacher
don't fit you maybe it fits your friend
maybe it doesn't fit you and don't be
shy just say I like you you look nice
you're
funny but I think I need a different
teacher you know that's okay that's fine
you know my teacher said
well there's not much Market in
America if you find one you better take
it anyway that's a joke okay LEL means
you met a good teacher uh la
this
is this is L this is the source of the
word L okay Lea the full word is
leura Ruma means fit or ready Le means
to do the work leum means ready to do
the work ready to do the work okay it's
like if you go to the gym and you want
to lift I don't know 20
kilos your your muscle has to be fit for
that weight if it's not you will hurt
yourself okay so laser means fit ready
for Spiritual work ready for Spiritual
work
L that's such a famous
word that uh Diamond way Retreat is
called
Lera okay and the short name is
Le okay Le so this is a very famous word
Diamond way
Retreat is called L okay classical L for
vaj guini take about three weeks okay
three weeks uh hard work maybe four
weeks okay we call L when you get a
empowerment into vaj guini you commit to
do four letters in your life okay four
uh three week
L uh and so this one means law Lawless
rumor your mind should be ready for the
work okay you should have a good teacher
but your State of Mind should be healthy
okay well
rested peaceful okay not a no big
arguments or fights with people your
mind should be ready Le means ready your
mind should be ready okay uh
receptive
T then to to do serious practice like
retreat uh you're going to need some
money okay he says stock you know
food uh place to stay you need diamond
mountain you need a good
Retreat cabin okay uh you cannot do deep
Retreat anywhere it it should be a
retreat cabin it's better okay uh it
should be in a beautiful place quiet
place and there should be a beautiful
cabin if people did Retreat there before
it's very good it's like Good Vibrations
okay so the cabin should be if the cabin
is built for Spiritual
Retreat then the feeling is going to be
much better okay and uh try to find a
place like that and and that means
sponsors you know you're going to have
to find someone to to pay and diamond
mountain
basically if you're serious uh we'll
find a way to to let you do a retreat
okay if you're
serious uh we'll try to help you to do a
retreat okay uh but don't just uh go
from your bedroom to your bathroom and
do a retreat it's better to get out to a
special Retreat House to do these two
three week Retreats okay start with with
two weeks start with three weeks then do
one month then do two months then do
three months then do six months then do
one year then do three years okay like
that then that's
enough okay all right uh K those people
at Diamond Mountain before I let them do
three-year Retreat I gave them seven
years of training seven years of
training to do a three-year Retreat okay
so don't get all excited about for year
Retreat okay one day of retreat with no
preparation is miserable three years of
retreat with no preparation is miserable
miserable miserable okay okay all right
you need training you need preparation
okay all right
say mulam de mulam de means you should
start making prayers that you
get these three supplies on the donkey
who's the donkey you
are what are the three supplies good
teacher and your mind is ready
trained and you have some support uh
from from good sponsors good people okay
sponsors are very important in Buddhism
and I know it sounds it's not nice to
talk about money it's not fun to talk
talk about
money if you want to do serious Retreat
it's expensive it it costs money you
know the food costs money and U things
like that the cabin costs money and it's
it's good to get it
ready okay all
right you want to hear a funny uh money
in Retreat joke this is why Grandpa is
so entertaining for
you uh so I have uh I was fortunate
uh when I started to learn yoga what
time am I supposed to finish Tim where
is Tim 20 minutes when I started to
learn yoga I was very lucky to get uh
two of the best teachers in the world
they are teaching pavarti they are
teaching
sting uh and uh this is David life and
Sharon Ganon great great yoga teachers
so they they train me to
do uh they train me to do yoga
uh because I was going to go into
three-year Retreat and I thought I
should learn to do some exercise in one
room because I mainly I didn't leave
that room for three years so and it's a
very small
room so I thought yoga is perfect
because I can do yoga inside the room so
I I I studied with them I learned how to
do they're good teachers they're very
strict hard teachers and I learned from
them and then I went into Retreat and I
asked them uh will
you uh agree to come and see me every
six months or something so I cannot talk
to them but they can talk to me and uh
there's a rule in Retreat your teacher
can come and see you teacher can come
and give you advice so they said okay we
will come and uh after six months
retreat they
came and uh
we had a
special year Mongolian house small one
for meeting teachers so they don't come
to my year they I go to the this meeting
urine okay and they we built a special
year for meetings with teachers and we
put a toilet next to it in the desert
you dig
down like 10 m and you dig down 10 m and
then you just have a small wooden house
with the one seat and a hole in the seat
you try not to fall down and uh we have
one like that and
uh and we have a rattlesnake who lives
at the
bottom you
know and uh they are very
poisonous and very dangerous and uh he
fell down he never came out
and he lived down there and when you sit
down you can hear
the but he cannot reach you you know
it's too far and uh anyway so David and
Sharon came to see see us and we sit in
the special place and they they killed
us you know this thing and they say bend
over and she took my hands and she put
it on the ground on the other
side you know I'm like ah you know and
she's like good you know she very tough
crazy tough you know and uh so then they
we did the yoga and and then they said
uh by the
way something bad happened and we're
[Music]
like and they say uh they run out of
money for your retreat there's no more
money for your retreat we're like
in Retreat your mind is very uh delicate
and you're
like and they this after one year six
months you know we're
like and they said don't
Ellie has
solution she has a we're
like and they say uh there's a I think
we had six retreatant or something she
said we will
rotate uh you come out out for one month
uh come out of retreat and work at
McDonald's and make some
money uh and support then every each
retrea will rotate out for one month two
months work at McDonald's we're were
like and then they said haha April
Fool
uh April first of April it's a joke in
America so you make a big joke to
somebody and they're like empa fools and
we're
like you know then after like two hours
Davis say I have to go peeee and we're
[Laughter]
like and we we we take him to this
special
toilet and he closed the door and we are
listening
you and then there's
M and he run out his pants are down it
was so
beautiful I we're
like so better to make sure you have the
money before you do
otherwise you're going to have some
problem that was so much fun
okay uh I think Q&A Tim am I right you
have any
time no but what's the
plan say
again does the Q&A supposed to start at
4 or
4:15 no but when was it supposed to
start he's so polite it's hard get him
to tell the
truth but the plan was
4:15 okay good so Q&A for 15 minutes
okay okay that I tried to time the joke
at the right
time okay uh three kinds of questions
number one about the topic which is
usually
unusual uh second if you have a personal
question uh I'm very happy to answer
question don't be shy listen I heard
every embarrassing question a hundred
times many people have done more
terrible things than you don't be so
proud you are number one okay
so any questions okay and then thirdly
if you have a philosophy question
emptiness question you're welome okay
I'll let you guys pick the
question thank you Goa for your teaching
I have a question about uh I heard about
a saying in the sura uh saying that the
outside world is aligned with our inner
world so like the star like the color
like the animal it all aligned with our
inner body organ or body parts um where
can we learn more about this I heard
that the color um CH color no the color
chakra was discussing about that I I
checked but I was not able to find it so
could you please elaborate more on this
and uh if we could make use of this then
it's much easier for us to work inside
cool yeah thank you very much sure uh
two comments uh number one um I think I
told the story to some I told all these
stories please be patient with me I
teach every day of the year almost and I
don't remember which story I told you
and which story I didn't tell you so
anyway I uh was
translating we have a book series called
classics of middle
Asia and this the mixnuts books are
these big major books Nick's book is 700
pages in fact it's two books because
it's too fat and um then we have
pocketbooks which are supposed to fit in
your purse or you can put in your pocket
and you can carry them uh around like I
used to take them to work and when I do
my lunch hour I will read this it's kind
of
easier uh Dharma books uh and I was uh
and we reprinting them Rosa is
reprinting them and they're on eBook now
so uh just came out
something both of there's two already
ready Gibson is working on two more and
uh so we we have these pocketbooks uh I
ran into some difficult translation in
the one of them uh it's actually a
Diamond W book and uh
I I couldn't understand the words there
were some strange words and I went to my
teacher I had a dictionary called my
teacher I never had a paper dictionary
or I I didn't need it I had my teacher
and uh I remember where he taught me
each word almost I can remember where I
was like we were in a coffee shop or
something and so I asked him uh I don't
understand these words and he said oh
don't worry those are astrology those
are astrology
words then I said wow Pabon Diamond way
attacks very deep astrology in the
middle uh because in my country
astrology has a bad name astrology is
like
hippie people who take your money and
they tell you anything you know oh Pluto
is in the eastern part of the sky that
means instead of $25 you have to pay me
$50 and then you're like what like we
don't like it h we feel mainly we feel
uncomfortable with it and I was
surprised I said wow astrology you know
and he said don't don't think it's
stupid it's very deep uh Buddhist
astrology is very very
deep and I said how and he said these
words are Buddhist astrology and there
was an astrology master in our Monastery
and he explained all those words to me
uh and
um I asked my teacher when do you study
astrology it's not part of the gishi
course he said only the person who
finished the gesi is allowed to study
astrology you know and it's like yoga
those two things you have to finish
gishi so I'm like wow so what is
Astrology and he
said it's from the colge chakra Tantra
it's Tantra it's secret teaching and he
said uh we have this onion skin
Theory like your body has a kernel and
then it has layers many layers you have
your physical body then you have your
pral body and you have your karma body
and you have your emptiness
body Chi body these are all like layers
of
onion and uh according to the inner
mental body and the Chi body the skin
and the bones will also change so the
this is your outside
envelope and then inside the envelope is
your mind and inside the mind is
emptiness and between there's the seeds
right so if the seeds are good the ches
is good if the ches is good the chakras
are good if the chakras are good the
body is good if the body is good the sky
is
good okay interesting the next envelope
it's very beautiful idea so it is
true that if you learn to read the stars
and the planets
correctly you can tell a lot about your
inner body okay so and that can tell you
a lot about your mind and so there is a
there is a system to pay attention to
that that's one answer and that takes a
lot of training and you have to find a
llama who knows call a chakra and it
takes a long time to learn those books
are some of the longest books in
Buddhism like kuub J wrote too I think
they're and they're difficult so you can
find a college chakra master and study
well with them it takes a long time
but uh there's a similar training coming
up on the next page of the
lojo
so just wait one
day and we'll talk about it tomorrow
it's coming tomorrow okay all right
[Applause]
okay okay how we doing on time Timothy
we
okay yeah
okay
for
[Music]
so basically uh one of her friends is in
sorry sorry uh my friend is in a coma
and uh their family might be making some
decisions of letting
uh letting him go yeah I've been uh
trying to plant seeds to stop his death
but it seemed that
um um nothing is working yet um I want
to ask how can I plant some powerful
seeds to really help my friend I'm sorry
um um from this um from this tragic yeah
okay good good
question we had a similar question
yesterday or the day before about uh
euthanasia
e
[Music]
for
if you could see the
house or if you could experience them if
you can read about them and you don't
really believe
them uh nobody believes it there's a
joke in the Christian religion that the
devil's greatest achievement in this
century is people don't believe in hell
you know and uh so but if you could
really see the hell and if you know
about this one you will keep everybody
alive as long as possible you know no
matter what you will keep them alive
whatever suffering they have in the
hospital whatever suffering they have in
the coma
is nothing compared to where they are
going if you could
see where they will be one hour later
nobody would ever kill
someone uh because the next place is
much much worse so it's in Buddhism if
if you really understand
Buddhism uh it's better to try to keep
them alive even if they are suffering
even if the suffering is very serious so
give them my father had it's called
brompton's
solution it's a Yin it's a cocaine and
morphine and give them cocaine morphine
keep them from having terrible pain but
don't kill them you know don't let them
die and I know that's a difficult answer
and I know it's not a popular
answer and uh I'm not afraid to give
unpopular answers maybe you and noticed
uh but uh that's the official Buddhist
uh position but D
uh you know if you don't really
accept uh health and you don't
understand
them and you just see the suffering of
the person and you and you understand
everybody understands there's no hope
for them
uh and you feel you want to stop their
pain
uh in my opinion if you do it with that
motivation it's good for you and it's
good for them in my opinion okay if if
your motivation
is pure and and you really want to help
them and you we say pull the plug if you
take out the you know the food or
something I I I believe personally uh
because of motivation is number one
motivation is always
99% if your motivation is good I believe
uh you make a good seed and uh I believe
if your motivation is pure you can help
it's possible you can help that person
uh then you should study
carefully all the best prayers and the
best practices to help them uh as they
die and uh they look like they are
unconscious but they can hear
something and they can feel something so
it's possible to help them uh if your
family decides to pull the plug and you
cannot stop them
uh I think to make everything peaceful
it's important that people die peaceful
and the family shouldn't be fighting in
the room or or disagree and so if the if
most of the
family doesn't understand Buddhism and
they want to end the person's life uh I
believe a real Buddhist can make it a
good thing I believe a real Buddhist can
can do powerful prayers and Powerful
prano practices and I believe if you're
well
trained uh you can help them a lot and
and so then so it's it's kind of depends
on the motivation and and I wouldn't
fight with your family you know I would
try to respect the family's wishes and
you're not going to change their mind in
in one year or something like that so I
think it's better that there should be
peace in the
family and if the person's dying they
can feel the emotions in the room
and so I think it's important that the
family is United and supportive of each
other and they're not fighting about
should we pull the plug or not and I
think that's more important yeah cool
[Applause]
yeah